## ALEXANDER MERKULOV

1426 Dogwood In, Huntingdon Valley, PA 19006 Phone: 215-380-1076 (US Citizen)

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Seasoned professional with more than 20 years of IT experience. Extensive exposure to the Oracle technology stack. Worked on numerous successful infrastructure as well as development projects in the technical lead role. Well versed in Unix scripting languages Korn/Bash, Perl, Python, PL/SQL, Java and numerous OS systems,. In-depth knowledge of Oracle internals. Good understanding of Cloud computing (AWS). Great troubleshooter and performance expert. In-depth knowledge of transactional and analytical database modeling for RDBMS and No-SQL databases. Expert query writer and data analyst. Self-starter who can work alone but also very much a team oriented individual who love to share knowledge and assure excellence in all his professional activities.

Certifications:
Oracle OCP
AWS Big Data (BDS)
AWS Solution Architect (SAA)
AWS SysOps Admin (SOA)

#### **EXPERIENCE**

# Cobham Advanced Electronics LLC. Lansdale, PA Sr. Database Engineer

10/2017 - 12/2017

- Assessment of the organizational readiness for the information security compliance audit to meet the DFRAS guidelines using the CIS cyber-security benchmarks for Oracle and MS SQL Server databases.
- Patching Oracle/MS SQL Server environments to the latest PSU/Security patches.
- Planning and implementation of the change management procedures to enable/implement recommended security controls: database parameter changes, user access, client/server parameter file configuration.
- Compiled of a waiver list for the security controls that couldn't be implemented for various reasons and/or have to be revisited in the future with a detailed explanation/justification of each given case.
- Troubleshooting ongoing technical issues.

# SunGard High Availability Services, Philadelphia PA Sr. Database Engineer (part time)

4/2017 - 7/2017

- DR test recoveries for various SunGard clients.
- Participated in various test data recoveries for Oracle and DB2 databases.
- Design and implementation of DR execution plans.
- Troubleshooting ongoing technical issues.

# Harte Hanks, Trevose PA Sr. Database Engineer/Technical Lead

9/2015 - 1/2017

- Responsible for the implementation of the DataMart solution for the Nation Wide insurance client.
- The role included the gap analysis and data cleansing of the old NW marketing provider Sigma Corp.
- Integration of the HH and Sigma data sources into a coherent historical view of the NW marketing campaigns.
- Documentation of the business requirements and creation of BRD and TRD documentation.
- Logical and physical modeling of DataMart schema. (Power Designer).
- Optimization and tuning of the ETL (ODI 12c) routines for loads of large volumes of data...
- Sorce/Target mappings. Extraction, cleansing, transformation and integration of the marketing data.
- Customization of the knowledge modules. Provisioning of the users (Security Manager).
- Configuration of the source and target system connections (Topology Manager).
- Tuning complex queries and PL/SQL packages.
- The evaluation and strategic planning for data processing/off-loading to AWS Redshift analytical workspace.
- End to end automation of the month-end data processing to AWS Redshift cluster instances (Lambda/CloudFormation)Python.
- Installation and configuration of Redshift cluster backup/advanced monitoring utilities.
- Code review and QA support of incremental software releases (SDLC).
- Defect identification and documentation. Source code version control. (JIRA/GIT).
- Database parameters tuning, performance problem analysis and resolutions.
- Daily interaction with developers, client stake holders, business analysts, system administrators and project managers to insure smooth and timely delivery of the project milestones.

# Children Hospital of Philadelphia, PA Sr. Database Engineer/Technical Lead

6/2014 - 6/2015

- Patching and upgrade of Oracle RAC clusters and Data Guard installations 11g R2/12c. AIX 6.1
- Maintenance and support of Clustered SQL Server databases.
- Conversion and expansion of Oracle RAC clusters.
- Support and implementation of Oracle Data Guard solution architecture.
- Troubleshooting of RAC installation and RAC performance issues.
- Participated in deployment configuration of the Oracle Could Grid infrastructure 12c.
- Troubleshooting of performance issues in clustered, DG and single instance environments.
- Review and enhancement of oracle administration scripts.
- Clarity Data Warehouse performance enhancement strategies and implementation.
- Migration of Clarity DW to Exadata platform.

- Tuning SQL and PL/SQL code.
- Support of the application development team in Java (ORM/Hibernate) based high volume transactional environments.
- Support of Oracle SOA/EBS implementation initiative.
- Liaison between the client and the Oracle critical account management team.
- Participated in 24/7 support of missions critical databases.

# J&J, Wayne, PA 1/2012-5/2014

# Sr. Database Engineer/Technical Lead

- Designed and implemented the DW project for a new J&J product.
- Assessment of the enterprise readiness and proposal of the implementation strategy.
- Implementation of the Cloud Solution architecture for AWS (Redshift).
- Selection of the technology stack for the infrastructure build (Oracle 11gR2, OBI ODI).
- Installation and configuration of the selected components.
- Implementation of the Oracle Database Vault security.
- Logical and physical design of the supporting database components (PowerDesigner).
- Design and implementation of a (PL/SQL) test data model for the system capacity planning and simulation of transactional system life cycle.
- Build of staging, historical and DW schemas using ETL(ODI).
- Full instrumentation and error handling of ETL processes.
- Parallelization of ODI load plans and packages.
- Customization of existing ODI knowledge modules.
- Design and implementation of BI reporting for Oracle BI, Tableau and Cognos platforms.
- Report design for various business customers Excel/Oracle Publisher.
- Implementation of Google Analytics API (Java/RESTfull) to merge GA data with the DW analytics workspace.
- Integration of Google Analytics data into the Data Warehouse environment.
- Business and functional requirements gathering and documentation.

# PJM interconnection, Norristown, PA Sr. Oracle DBA

9/2009-12/2011

- Maintenance and support of mission critical databases (Oracle, SQL Server)
- Migration and upgrades from 10.1.0.5/10.2.0.4 to Oracle 11gR2.
- FS to ASM migrations.
- Maintenance and support of Oracle E-Business suite applications.
- Support of Oracle Exadata databases.
- Implementation of 11g Grid Control with concentration on patching Oracle databases, development of custom reporting and management plug-ins.
- Implementation of Golden Gate replication solutions.
- Implementation of Oracle Database Vault security.
- Development of Database monitoring and administrative interfaces. (Apex).
- Tuning and enhancement of Oracle PL/SQL packages.
- RAC/DG with Golden Gate support.
- Was providing support and administration of the Data Warehouse environment. Tuning and modifications of ETL processes (Informatica) and BI reporting solutions (OBIEE).

• Core DBA duties and responsibilities in 24x7 environment.

# Shire Pharmaceuticals, Wayne, PA Senior Oracle Enterprise/Architect/Technical Lead

8/2008-9/2009

- Responsible for Oracle enterprise re-architecture project in Shire Pharma Chesterbrook office.
- The project involved creation of HA Oracle enterprise environment on Linux RHEL 5 platform running Oracle version 10.2.0.4.
- Migration of existing Oracle databases from Windows single instance to RAC on Linux.
- Deployment of Grid Control in HA configuration.
- Deployment of DataGuard in HA configuration.
- Implementation of backup and recovery policies and procedures.
- Standardization of Oracle installation and configuration in HA environment.
- Customization and extension of Oracle Grid monitoring environment:
- Custom backup reports, custom database instance efficiency reports, custom storage utilization reports.
- Use of Oracle CRS capabilities to integrate with third party applications.

# Barclays Bank, Wilmington, DE Senior Oracle Production DBA/Technical Lead

7/2007-6/2008

- Performance troubleshooting, maintenance, patching and upgrades of the Barclays financial warehouse.
- Root cause analysis of the warehouse critical performance issues.
- New infrastructure build and migration of the DW from the Sun OS to the AIX platform in HA configuration.
- Support and troubleshooting of performance issues with batch job operations (DataStage), ad-hoc queries (SAS), BI reporting (Brio).
- Monitoring and improvement of the data warehouse physical storage layout recommendations and implementation of changes for storage reorganization.
- Infrastructure recommendations and transition plans to meet the accelerating business growth forecasts.
- Support of the Database Architecture Team in developing solutions for data replication into the lower environments with data masking, transparent data encryption and Oracle database Vault technologies.
- Improvement and enhancement of the enterprise monitoring infrastructure OEM/Nagios.'
- 24/7 support of mission critical databases.

# Department of Defense, DSCP - 6B430, Philadelphia, PA General Dynamics Information Technology Oracle Application DBA/Technical Lead

11/2006-5/2007

- Maintenance and support of the DOD mission critical databases.
- Design and implementation of the back-end driven workflow engine to serve a collaborative documentation management among different DOD clients PL/SQL.
- Data object modeling, data mapping, gap analysis and system design (Power Disigner).
- Assessment of the enterprise readiness for SOA and BPM solution architecture.
- Tuning Oracle packages and SQL ad-hoc queries.
- Extraction and Load of Oracle data into Sql Server databases. (SSIS).
- Development and optimization of business reports for gathering the system performance metrics using Visual Studio 2005 report designer (SSRS)/Excel.

# J&J, Titusville, New Jersey Oracle DBA specialized

- Design and implementation of large data replication processes (PL/SQL).
- Utilization of SMP capabilities through the alignment of data partitioning design with multiple execution threads.
- Program interface implementation in Korn and Perl scripting languages.
- Optimization of back-end reporting processes: Prescriber View, Volume Share, Managed Markets and Call Activity reports(PS/SQL).
- Integration of IMS data into Sibel Analytics work space (Informatica).
- Business report rewrites to optimize the run-times and deliverable deadlines.

# General Dynamics, Philadelphia PA Oracle DBA/Data Architect

6/1999-10/2005

- Installation of Oracle software, testing releases of new patches and software upgrades (Windows/Linux).
- Development of monitoring shell scripts for reporting on various high priority database areas.
- Monitoring and tuning of database instances (Windows NT/Sun Solaris).
- Backup and recovery strategies (RMAN) on Windows and Linux platforms.
- Administration and support for Oracle Discoverer.
- Logical and physical design of EPA OLTP and DSS systems.
- Coding database access layer PL/SQL.
- Synchronization of production data with lower environments.
- Developed ETL replication architecture for divisional financial reporting systems (Oracle DW builder).
- Design, maintenance and integration of EPA Enterprise wide financial data system for Superfund.
- Data migrations for the Air division from dBase database into Oracle 8i.
- Data migrations of the billing tracking system for Superfund division from Clipper to Oracle RDBMS.
- Data migration of the billing tracking system for the Water division from Access to Oracle RDBMS.
- Was responsible for creating the system and user documentation

# Assessment System INC. West. Bala Cynwyd, PA Senior Programmer Analyst

5/1997-5/1999

- Development and support of RES2000 (Booking of seats for testing) application PL/SQL Oracle 8.
- Developed and implemented new system packages and procedures for processing new client-candidate data
- Created a set of utilities for transferring client data from production to development databases environments.
- Developed stored procedures for the multiple database support (AllBase, Oracle, SQLServer).
- Developed the client authorization file loan programs written in C and Pro\*COBOL.
- Developed an application for printing wallet cards and wall licenses for the Florida Insurance Department.

# MORTGAGE MANAGEMENT CORP., Trevose, PA

9/1994-4/1997

# **Programmer Analyst**

- Development and support of an accounting application designed to manage mortgage portfolios.
- Implementation of the back-end application code for the voucher creation, cash receipts, debit and credit processing.
- Development of stored procedures (Sybase, Oracle, DB2) for clients using different RDBMS platforms.
- Deployment of the application code to clients using different platforms using Unix shell scripts.

- Creation and support of the software intended for the internal company use, account payable/receivable, inventory and report processing.
- Rewrites of outdated DOS programs and their deployment in the Client/Server based architecture system.
- Multiple database support Oracle, Sybase, DB2 RDBMS, back-end programming and logical database design.

#### UNIVERSITY OF DNEPROPETROVSK, Ukraine

1/1992-2/1994

Department of Linguistic and Information Technology Linguistic Analyst

- Participated in design and implementation of software for comparative language analysis (COBOL/FORTRAN).
- Was responsible for developing different structural patterns that were applied as filters to different group of languages to determine their existing similarities on the level of the morphological structure.

#### **EDUCATION & DEVELOPMENT**

# Dnepropetrovsk State University, Dnepropetrivsk, Ukraine

BA in Linguistic, minor in Information Technology.

#### InfoSource Technical School, Philadelphia, PA

In-house and professional Seminars: Oracle 7 for application developers, Client/Server computing, Complex SQL queries, developing applications with PowerBuilder and Oracle. Curriculum concentration on PC Application Development: MS-DOS, Windows, Relational Database Concepts, and SQL Programming.

#### InfoSource Institute, Philadelphia, PA

Oracle 8 advanced course, advanced features of Oracle 8 database, database architecture, introduction into database administration and recovery on Windows NT.

#### InfoSource Technical School, Philadelphia, PA

Oracle 8i Development and Tuning Training program

2003 In-house training on concepts and designs of Oracle 9i data warehouse.

# Certificates

Oracle 8i-9i-10g-11g OCP AWS Solution Architect Associate.